Hello, and welcome back to another
video with itsDrdan, and today
we're going to be practicing
balancing nuclear decay equations.
which you find in nuclear chemistry.
Um, we're also going to be going into
fission and fusion, and then we're also
going to be wrapping this into half life.
So it's going to be a really broad
overview of all the different skills
that you gain in your nuclear chemistry
chapter, um, really evolving around
isotopes and all these different things
that you've learned about throughout
the, throughout your semesters, and how
to really utilize your periodic table
to We're going to be looking at mainly
all the different examples of this and
then eventually leading up to fission
and fusion and how we can try to figure
out what can happen when you have
multiple reactions occurring one after
another in a essential and a covalent
Chain reaction of one after another.
So let's take a look at all these
different practice problems.
The first thing is, is when it
comes to balancing a nuclear decay
equation is that you got to remember
the law of conservation of mass.
Is that mass cannot be
created nor destroyed.
So you have to have the same
amount of mass on both sides.
Now, when we are doing this, we're
always going to be adding up protons
and neutrons and really trying to see
exactly how much of everything do we have.
So for this particular one, we,
one thing we always want to be
practicing is can you identify.
what kind of process this is.
So we have fr which is franzium and
it's franzium 850 or sorry 215 and
this is also going via positron decay.
So as you can see we have a little
beta plus which represents a
positron and then zero and plus one.
So what that means is when we're
looking at this is the two top parts
that are the atomic mass should equal
the left hand side which is 215.
So what we're going to have is 0,
and when we add that to 215, we'll
see those two numbers will match.
So we know that the left and
the right equal each other.
Now when we do the same thing
for the bottom, right, we see
on the left hand side that it
equals a total of 87 on the left.
So what does that mean?
That the total here should
also equal a total of 87.
How would I do that?
Well, if we take 87 and then subtract
a 1 from that, that's going to be 86.
So if I take 86 plus one,
that will be a total of 87.
But now what we got to do is figure out,
well, what, what element is number 86?
So that's when we go to a periodic
table and we have to check.
So this is where we got to kind of look
all over it and try to find number 86.
which we'll see is like
all the way down here.
So this is radon is number 86.
So that is going to be the one that
we're going to be using right here.
So radon is number 86.
So for these, you're always going
to need your periodic table.
So you, it will help you kind of,
really find all the different,
um, different elements that you
probably don't really see that often.
Cause a lot of times you're very,
very high number elements on a lot
of these equations, not all the
time, but many of them are the ones
that are in the F series, transition
states, the very unstable species.
So if we have another one,
so in this case, we have a
beta decay that's occurring.
So we have copper 66 and it's going
to be going through beta decay.
So what that means, we're going
to do the same type of thing.
So the atomic mass has to
be the same on both sides.
So being that we have 66 on the left, we
should have a total of 66 on the right.
So we see that 66 plus
zero is equal to 66.
And on the bottom, we have 29.
So once again, our tire right hand
side should also be equal to 29.
So if we take, if we try to do some
little math here, how can we get 29?
Well, if we do 30 minus
1, that will give us 29.
Okay, so we're going to be adding
up all these little pieces.
to try to make the left and
the right equal each other.
So once again, what are we going to do?
We're going to go to our periodic table
and we're going to be trying to find
element number 30, element number 30.
And what we can see is it's always going
to be really close to where you started.
So we have copper that's right
here, but you can see that
right next door is number 30.
Which is going to be zinc.
What element or what nucleide that
we're going to be starting with, right?
So it says what we have 129 Te so this
is your parent nucleide and what it's
telling us is that's gonna go through
Alpha decay which if you remember we
represent by a helium atom Which is 4,
2 with an He and if you don't remember
all these go to my types or react
different types of reactions video To
help review all these core concepts
Now, we want to know is what will, what
will we create once this breaks apart?
So we're going to be creating
a new species, just like how
we had in the previous problem.
So the one thing that we got to do is kind
of fill in all the missing boxes, right?
So we have, you got to have an
atomic mass and an atomic number
for every single element here.
So we got to fill those in.
So the first thing we should
do is let's fill in tellurium.
So, Te is all the way down here, this is
tellurium, so you can see it's right here.
So this is number 52
on our periodic table.
So what we're going to do here is
we're going to write in a big 52.
to match our periodic table.
And now what that's going to tell
us is that, okay, the entire bottom,
all the atomic numbers, should have
a total of 52, because the left and
the right should match each other.
So how do we get 52?
We do 50 plus 2, and that's going to
give us the identity of our element.
Now when we do our next part, well
we got to remember that when we're
looking at all these different pieces
of the puzzle trying to figure out
what our element is, Well, we got
to also add up our masses as well.
So being that the left hand side is
equal to a total of one 29 for the
atomic mass, that means the right
also has to equal up to one 29.
So if I take one 25 plus four.
That equals 129.
So now what I'm going to now do is look
for number 50 on our periodic table.
So it's kind of like kind of a
game where you're always trying
to find all the missing pieces.
And then we can see that 10 is really
close to it, which is 50, which is
the identity, which we go off the
number of protons in our nucleus.
Okay.
So that's one thing to kind of keep
in mind is that when we're looking
at all these, we can always see that
everything is kind of changing, right?
So we have 50 protons here.
52 protons and we also see the number
of neutrons is changing as well.
So we have 75 neutrons on this
side and then a total of 77
neutrons on the other side.
So you see that lost two neutrons,
two protons in this transition.
So you can always kind of count to make
sure that everything's equal, especially
if the figure out some of those harder
problems, which might involve subatomic
particles and counting everything.
It goes back to your basics of,
can you read a periodic table and,
uh, and answer all these questions.
So, our next problem is write the nuclear
equation for iron 59, which undergoes
beta and gamma emission simultaneously.
Okay, so being that we have iron 59,
so the first thing is, being that it's
written that What that's telling us
is that is the mass of iron, right?
It's not referring to the number, it is
the atomic mass of this radioisotope.
So, we're going to write iron 59, and it's
telling us that we're doing two different
emission processes at the same time.
We have a beta emission, so
that's zero, negative one.
And then we also have gamma emission.
And these are the kind of things I
would really recommend, uh, kind of
memorizing for your exams, because
usually you're not given these four.
Um, they are pretty easy symbols to
remember, but it's still one more thing
to kind of add to the, add to the puzzle.
So, now what we're trying to do is figure
out is, what is our missing pieces?
So we're trying to figure out what is the
daughter nucleide that is created, and
remember the left has to equal the right.
So, the first thing we should do is
we should look up iron, right, so iron
is number 26 on our periodic table.
So we're going to end up kind of
writing that down for ourselves,
seeing that that is number 26.
So once we write that in, just to kind of
fill in that gap, so 26, that means that
our, all the numbers on the bottom here,
adding up all three of these, should have
a total of 26, and the entire total of
the atomic mass should be equal to 59.
So if I am to do that, well the nice thing
is, is on the bottom, how do I get to 26?
Well, if I do 27 plus negative 1, That's
going to give us our missing number.
So this is going to be
an atomic number of 27.
Now, being that everything is zeros
on the top here for all of our
masses, that is really easy math.
So all we have to do is just fill in
that missing number there, which is
going to be 59 for our missing box.
So 59 will be our mass.
So let's try to figure
out what number 27 is.
So it's going to be really close to iron.
That's going to be right next door to it.
And I have it kind of
covered up with my box.
And you're going to see that it is cobalt.
Cobalt is number 27.
All right, so we're going to fill
that in, that we have cobalt.
And now, well, what is exactly
happening here in this process?
Well, the one thing when you have a
beta decay, it's going to be changing
your protons and neutrons around.
And then gamma emission, it's going
to be releasing a high energy photon.
So well, what exactly is happening here?
Well, if you count your, your
different, uh, subatomic particles.
Right, you have 26 protons that are here,
and then if you can calculate how many
neutrons there are by subtracting it by
the number of your atomic mass, and you'll
get that there's 33 neutrons in iron.
So if you look now at cobalt, well,
how did the entire picture change?
Well, you have 27 protons over here.
So what you're going to have is a neutron
is going to convert into a proton.
So you see that the neutron
count went down and then the
proton count went up as a result.
And that's beta.
So with positron is the opposite one
of instead a proton is going to be
converted into a neutron instead.
And that's where that
positive particle comes from.
Um, and when it's releasing
that anti antimatter.
Let's take a look at another example.
Sometimes you're going to have bombardment
reactions, which is a really common
reaction that's done in synchrotrons
around the country and around the world.
So what a synchrotron is, is
essentially when you have particles
that are accelerated very, very
fast, um, essentially approaching
the speed of light across miles.
So there's these facilities
around the world.
There's one at CERN in Switzerland and
another one in Berkeley in California.
that accelerate different particles to try
to see if they can collide them with each
other to see if we can make new elements.
So one of the things is that when
you have these collision problems,
it's a little bit more involved
because you'll have multiple reactants
and also multiple products because
pieces are going to be breaking off.
We're going to be splitting
the atom essentially.
So what we're going to be doing is
the same idea is we're going to be
adding up the top and the bottom.
Right, so when we do this, we usually
always have one complete side.
So what you can see on the products
is we have both products here.
So we have that, we have argon, it's
colliding with something and it's
going to be breaking down into a
potassium 43 and a proton, right?
So this guy, I know it shows hydrogen,
but we always think of this as a proton.
So whenever we are looking
at, at that species.
So we have a total of 44 as our mass.
So that means we need
44 on the left as well.
So being that we have 40 on the left,
if we do 44 minus 40, that tells
you you're missing a total of 4.
Now on the bottom, we have a
total of 20 when we do 19 plus 1.
So that means we need 20 also
on the left hand side too.
So if we do 18 plus 2,
that's going to be a total.
So which subatomic particle or
what element does that represent?
Well, one thing that you can realize
is, hey, that's helium, right?
So helium or an alpha particle.
So that tells you a really big, heavy
alpha particle collided with argon to
break it into potassium and hydrogen.
So sometimes you have word
problems and it doesn't give you
all the, all the little pieces.
So let's break down this word problem.
So it says carbon 11 is bombarded.
Okay.
So being that we have the word carbon 11.
Let's start by writing that down.
So we know it's C11 and you know that it's
atomic number 6 from the periodic table.
Now when it says it's being bombarded,
that means it's colliding with something.
Something is reacting with it.
Okay, so those are like
those little buzzwords.
So we'll put the word reacting
just so it's something that's,
that you're familiar with.
Now it's saying it's colliding with
a helium 4, so it's telling you that,
alright, we're going to be reacting
with another helium, and then it says,
as a result, we're going to be making
a proton, so we see that we're making a
proton, so what we'll do is we'll draw
an arrow, and We'll put a single proton
here and one other particle is produced.
Okay, so what we're trying to do is
figure out is what is the other particle.
So with that being said, what we're
going to do is the same process
that we've been doing before.
So when we look at this, we're
going to add up what we have
on the left side this time.
So when I add up my masses, I
have a total of 15 on the top.
And then when I add up my atomic
numbers, I have a total of 8.
So this is going to be what we're going
to have also on the right hand side.
So we're going to have a total
of 8 on the bottom as well.
So that means what's, how do I get to 8?
Well, we do 7 plus 1, that will give us 8.
So we can see that we have that total.
And then when it comes to the
bottom, well, how do we get to 15?
Well, we got to do 14 plus
1 is going to give us 15.
Okay, so we have that same total.
Now which element is number seven?
Well, what's one away from carbon?
And it's nitrogen, right?
So when we take a radioactive carbon, hit
it with a helium or an alpha particle,
it's going to make a stable nitrogen.
Remember the goal of all
nuclear decay is to make stable
isotopes eventually over time.
So that would be our answer.
Let's take a look at another example.
Gallium is used for the tech
detection of pancreatic cancer
because it's taken up by tumors.
The emission of positrons allows
the tumor to be located in when
it comes to medical imaging.
So let's first write the
balance equation for this.
So what it tells you is that we're
gonna have gallium, Gallium 68
is what's going to be used here.
So let's first write that down,
and then it says it's going
through positron emission.
Well when we're doing something with
positron emission, that's going to
be 0 and plus 1 with a beta plus.
And now we wanted to try to figure out is,
well, what species is going to be created?
Well, the one thing we can remember is,
well, the tops are going to be equal.
So that's a pretty easy one,
being that a positron has no mass.
So that means the mass of our new
particle is also going to be 68.
Now, you're probably trying
to think, well, what's the
atomic number for gallium?
Well, that's why we have periodic tables.
We look these things up.
So the one thing is you can
see gallium is right here.
It has a mass of 31, or sorry,
not a mass, atomic number of 31.
So what we are going to do is
we're going to write a 31 here.
So that means that the higher bottom
of this should equal to 31 as well.
So if I take 30, add that to 1, we get 31.
Which different element is 30?
So we're going to look right next door.
And we see, hey, look, it's zinc.
So zinc, again, zinc 30 is going to be
our isotope here that is going to be made.
Now let's try to combine this
kind of problem with something
else that we've done before in the
past, which is half life reactions.
So when it comes to trying to do these
kinds of reactions with medical imaging
and different We have to consider how
long does it live within the body or
within our world before you choose
it for something that could last for
maybe just a few minutes or a few hours
or days or years or millennia, right?
We have to consider how long does it live.
Let's take a look.
So with this problem, if the half
life of the reaction above is 68
minutes, how much of a 64 microgram
sample is active after 136 minutes?
So half lives, they tie into these
types of radioactive decay as well.
To remind you, what was a half life?
The half life of a radioisotope is the
time for the radiation level to decrease,
or decay, half of its original amount.
So every single radioisotope has
a time frame where that occurs.
So what that means, after every half
life, it's going to decrease by half.
So if I started 100 percent on my sample,
I'll have 50, then I'll have 25, then
I'll have 12 and a half, and so forth,
and it'll keep continuing, right?
It'll be half, a quarter, an eighth,
and so forth, a sixteenth, and so forth
for every single half life that passes.
It's going to be very,
very little in the end.
So let's try to solve this problem
that we were just looking at.
So the first thing that we got
to do is we have to write out,
well, how much sample did we have?
And it says that we have
64 micrograms of sample.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to write out our half lives and try to
see, well, when do we get to 136 minutes?
So the one thing is that you
could do is we could, uh, simply
just take that 136 minutes.
And then see if it divides cleanly into
our half lifetime, which was 68 minutes.
So if we do that, right,
we see we have 68 minutes.
We see that our total
time pass was 136 minutes.
So all these things can be used.
So if it divides cleanly, then we
can do this a lot simpler, right?
We don't have to use these, uh,
fancy kinetics equations that
you learn about in Gen Chem 2.
Right, that's beyond the
scope of this course.
So what we'll do is we need
to have two half lives.
So after the first half life,
it's going to divide by half.
So what we have is 32
micrograms after one half life.
Now after the second half life,
you're going to divide that by
in half again, so 32 micrograms.
Divide by two, and then we'll have
a total of 16 micrograms, and that's
going to be how much is left and
remaining with inside your sample.
So it's all about, well,
how much is active?
It's going to be 16 micrograms,
and it went through two half
lives when that happened.
And so essentially you can kind of
see is that each part, right, we had
a half of our at the middle, and now
we're down to a quarter of our sample
after the second half life, and then
if you went through another one, it'd
be at an eighth, then a sixteenth,
then a thirty second, and so forth.
It's gonna keep getting smaller
and smaller and smaller.
Let's look at another example.
Technetium is used in over 80 percent
of all nuclear medicine procedures.
The isotope has a half life of only 6
hours, so it makes it really good for
something when you have to do medical
imaging, or if you want to keep a patient
overnight for observations, or to bring
them in over multiple times over the
course of a week, you can really track the
progress of how this isotope will work.
Now, if the patient is given a
dosage that has an activity of 8.
0 millicuries, when will
the activity become 0.
50 millicuries?
Now what the heck is a Curie?
I never talked about that in any video.
Well, let's look at it real quick.
There are units when it comes to actually
talking about radiation for when we're
trying to understand some of the basics.
I wrote some of them here.
The first one is the activity.
So when we talk about activity, we
usually look at it in two different units.
The common unit is a Curie named after
Marie Curie, the woman who founded and
won the Nobel Prize for radiation and
discovered multiple radioactive elements.
So what it means is one curie tells
you how many times an isotope is
disintegrating over a course of a second.
So usually it's always how much
is, uh, a gram disintegrates
within a second is usually the
way that's always referred to as.
So what we say is one curie is equal to 3.
7 times 10 to the 10
disintegrations per second.
Now, there's also the SI
unit, which is a Becquerel.
So whenever we use a Becquerel, it's a
Bq, and then one Becquerel is equal to 3.
7 times 10 to the 10
disintegrations per second.
Um, there's also absorbed doses.
So one is if you've ever seen
like the fallout show, which
is really popular right now.
Um, and then probably in a few years,
that might be a data reference, but right.
Absorbed dose is referred to as a rad.
So how much radiation have you absorbed?
Or if you have a gray, or a gray
is the SI unit, so it's joules per
kilograms of tissue that absorbs,
so it's the energy absorbed.
Now, does that mean you have
to do any crazy calculations?
You can treat them the exact same
way that you did with grams or
any type of sample you had before.
It's still going to be
half of what's there.
So, um, being that it wants to know how
many half lives occurred in order to get
from 8 to 0, what were, sorry, 5, 5, 5, 5.
What we're going to do
is map this guy out.
So we have 8.
0, then we'll go into
half, we'll go down to 4.
0, we'll do half again,
that's going to be 2.
0, okay.
Now we'll do another half, we're
dividing that by 2 one more
time, right, and we have 1.
0.
Now if we divide 1 by 2, we'll have our 0.
5, which was our goal.
Now, the question is, well, how
many, how many half lives is that?
Well, we'll count them, right?
We have one, two, three, four.
So you count each of those arrows.
Now, you gotta keep in mind, every single
one of those half lives is six hours.
So we're gonna have six plus six plus six.
So how many total hours have
passed over the course of time?
You'll add them all up, and you'll
see that 24 hours have passed.
in order to go from 8 to 0.
5 millicuries.
Okay, so that's going to be
MCI is what that unit is.
If you ever see a curie, you
can treat it like a gram when it
comes to a half life calculation.
It's going to still be divided
by half the whole time.
Now there are, it does have a different
meaning to it, but you can treat it the
same when you're doing these calculations.
All right, now let's go on to a
different type of problem altogether.
So with nuclear fission, so this type
of topic is something that's completely
different than anything we've looked at.
This one I think is just a little
bit of a little bit something
extra, so that way you know what the
difference in fission and fusion is.
So nuclear fission is essentially
what has caused the atomic bomb,
and it also is what causes us to be
able to power nuclear power plants.
So it goes from either energy
or a weapon of mass destruction.
And being that Oppenheimer is such a
big movie right now, it's kinda cool
to be able to kinda get an idea of
what the basic idea of the science is.
So what's actually
occurring within the bomb?
What do they actually have?
Well, the whole idea is that
inside of it, there is a bunch
of uranium that is inside.
And this is a essentially to uranium 235.
And then it's just it's
sitting inside the container.
It's not going to do
anything just being in there.
The thing is, it needs to be activated.
Now how is that actually done?
Well, what it, what happens is
they essentially shoot a neutron.
at the uranium atom or isotope.
When that happens, then
it becomes unstable.
The entire thing cannot
last in this condition.
It's going to explode and release
a ton of energy as a result.
So once that neutron gets shot in
there, it's going to be really unstable.
And the goal is to make stable isotopes.
So it's going to split into two
different, completely different isotopes.
And in the process release three
different neutrons as a result.
Now is that something
that's so crazy, right?
It releases a ton of energy
as a result, but is that all?
Well, essentially the way that that
works when it comes to a bomb is
it's all about a chain reaction.
And the same thing if you want to
actually cause a nuclear reaction
within a reactor to produce energy.
It's all about, well,
once I have the first one.
Can I have the reaction keep going
right where it keeps increasing, right?
So if one goes and they release
neutrons spontaneously, can it
hit another set of uraniums?
Which will then cause it to cascade
and cause More of these different
elements to split releasing more
neutrons and that will keep going
over and over and over again Have in
many of these different reactions.
So what the whole idea is when it comes to
creating nuclear energy is it's all about
the rapid increase in the number of high
energy neutrons that are created, right?
So every time when you have one, it
will split into three, which will
split into another set of three.
So you can kind of see it's
like a cube function of how fast
this thing is going to grow.
Now, in order to sustain this reaction.
All the uranium must be brought to
very, very close together, right?
So if you think of like the uranium,
uh, nuclear bomb, it was all kept in a
very, very tight capsule in order for
it to go very, very fast and release
a ton of energy all at the same time.
So now, when it's all brought
together, this is what's
referred to as the critical mass.
Meaning that essentially we're
going to have an almost immediate
collision with more neutrons.
Now when it comes to a nuclear
reactor, is it going to explode?
No, it's in a controlled process.
So that way it's a continuous
set of collisions and it'll
keep releasing energy.
Every time these different elements split,
you're going to be releasing energy,
which can be harvested and used as long
as everything's cooled down and properly
maintained in their safety conditions.
We can use it.
So it's all about hitting it
with a neutron and splitting.
So it's just something a little
bit different to learn about.
Let's learn about fusion.
So when it comes to fusion, the
whole idea here is this is actually
what causes our sun to shine
bright and the stars around us.
So this is a little bit of a
happier one, but it is something
that releases a ton of energy.
The sun releases so much energy that
you can feel it from earth, right?
We are very many, many millions
of miles away from the sun and you
can feel the heat coming off of it.
It releases a lot of energy.
So the whole idea here is when
you have two small nuclei that
combine to form a bigger nucleus.
Now, in the process, there is mass
that is lost, but it's all converted
to a massive amount of energy.
Now, this is even, this
is much more than fusion.
It's not even close in comparison.
Um, in fact, when it comes to fusion,
it requires temperatures around a
hundred million degrees Celsius.
Keep in mind when it comes to the
earth, generally we're anywhere
from like zero to what, like 40
degrees C typically in most climates.
Okay.
That's a lot.
So now the whole reason it has to be
that hot is that it needs to overcome the
repulsion within the atoms because we're
using two different nucleuses together.
That's extremely difficult
to do, especially under,
depending on the conditions.
Now when this happens, this
reaction is occurring continuously
in all stars and suns.
So once it starts, it doesn't stop.
So this is something that will keep going
for, for a very, very long period of time.
Eventually, it can run out,
but that's something that takes
millions and millions of years.
So the whole idea with this reaction
is when you take isotopes of hydrogen
and they, then they react together.
So if you didn't realize there are three
different major isotopes of hydrogen,
there's the normal one with just one
proton, but there's also deuterium,
which has an atomic mass of two as one
neutron, and then tritium, which has two
neutrons and then the one proton to it.
So when tritium and
deuterium combine together.
They're going to make a helium
atom and release a neutron and
a ton of energy in the process.
Now with that, that is what
the whole idea of fusion is.
So let's see if we do one practice
problem and see, can you identify
the two different types of reactions?
So if I ask you just to classify which
one is fusion or fission, could you do it?
So the idea of when it's fusion,
you have two different nucleides
coming together and it's going to be
making something, a bigger nucleus.
When it's fission, you have
a neutron being shot at it
and it's colliding with it.
So with this case, right on this
first one, you see that we have
these two small nuclei coming
together, fusing together, right?
It has to be small nuclei.
So in this first example, being
that we have two heliums, This
is what we consider as fusion.
They are coming together and it's
releasing some protons in the process.
Whereas the second one here, you can see
a neutron is being shot at a uranium and
it's splitting into different different
isotopes and releasing neutrons,
which will continue to chain react.
So this one is fission.
Luckily, I'm, I'll never ask you guys in
my class to ever balance these things.
Um, they're a little too major for
that, but it's good for you to be
aware of them because they can be
as some homeworks and quizzes and
sometimes on exams in the final.
So just be aware of that these two exist.
All right, so this has been
my practice problem video.
So went over everything that
you need to know for when it
comes to nuclear chemistry.
Um, I hope that it helped going over
many different types of examples,
hopefully prepares you for your
homework and your exams and all
these other different things.
Um, and I hope you got to learn
something new with this chapter.
So this wraps up nuclear chemistry.
So once again, thank you
so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped
a little bit for you to kind
of wrap up those loose ends.
Um, and if you did struggle with
watching it, I recommend watching
it and try solving it, pausing
while you're going through it, and
it'll help you really figure it out.
Um, and thank you once again.
If it's your first time here, please
hit that like and subscribe button, and
I hope to see you again in the future.
Alright?
Thanks all, I hope you
have a wonderful day.
I'll see you later.
Bye now.